hey what's up guys my name is eternal
welcome back to my C++ series so today
we're gonna be talking all about
multi-dimensional arrays in C++ 2d
arrays three arrays 40 erase doesn't
matter how many dimensions we have I'm
just calling the multi-dimensional
arrays because you can have as many
dimensions as you want first of all if
you haven't seen my video on arrays
definitely check that out because I
don't want to waste time explaining what
an array actually is we're just
specifically going to focus on
multi-dimensional arrays and also
definitely check out my video on
pointers if you haven't already pointers
are really important when you're doing
with arrays of any kind because arrays
are just blobs of memory and really is a
way for us to deal with memory is by
using pointers so definitely check it
out
okay so multi-dimensional arrays how
they differ from regular arrays and why
do we have them why don't we use them
why maybe shouldn't we use them
sometimes
so multi-dimensional arrays we'll start
with a 2d array two-dimensional array as
an example really all it is is just an
array of arrays and then if you have a
3d array it's an array of array of
arrays right so a two-dimensional array
is an array of arrays what I mean by
that is it's literally a collection of
arrays so if we think about one one of
our kind of strategies for dealing with
arrays is essentially by using a pointer
so we have a pointer to the beginning of
the array as it appears in our memory
that's how we kind of that's how we deal
with an array in this case right so if
you picture that
and then you picture an array of those
pointers what you kind of end up with is
I have a bunch I have a buffer in my
memory which contains consecutive kind
of pointers and each one of those
pointers points to a array some way in
my memory so we went on with is a
collection of pointers to erase an array
of a race right and we're gonna jump
into some civil spots go to actually
take a look at this because it can be a
lot easier than trying to visualize it
but that's basically what you end up
with so if I come over here into my card
what I'm going to do is just hip
allocate a simple array to begin with
just so that we're all on the same page
let's just say I allocate 50 integers
over here
I'm just using a cape allocation for now
with this is going to be easy to explain
because we got a point on straight away
and it's just a bit more power and what
this actually is if I want to have a two
dimensional array what I'm going to do
is have a pointer of pointers because
what I'm actually storing here is going
to be a buffer of pointer objects right
so this is a pointer to a collection of
int pointers this is where it gets a
little bit tricky because the allocation
of two-dimensional arrays in C++ is some
it's not really that straightforward in
other languages like C sharp or Java you
can just kind of it will just it'll
allocate all the memory that it needs
true for you and it's really easy to
deal with with say plus plus is not
because notice here what we've actually
done we've changed from just having a
pointer to an integer to having a
pointer to a pointer to an integer so
we've got a pointer to an integer
pointer now not to an actual integer
that's really really important because
in this case we're building a 32-bit
application so what we actually end up
with is a pointer and integer being the
same size but if we had an actual like
class or a struct or something that was
20 bytes large for example then in the
first case what we're actually doing is
we're allocating 50 20 byte chunks right
which essentially ends up with us having
a thousand bytes of allocated memory
whereas here what we're doing is we're
allocating 50 pointers so 50 times force
is 200 bytes of memory it's a completely
different allocation size and if you
actually look at this code and I'll kind
of I'll say I can't call to the array
I'll just call it a 2d array to do
terrible naming I know what we're
actually doing here is we're allocating
50 integer pointers so room for us to
store 50 integer pointers that's all
this is the actual arrays that we're
storing haven't actually been allocated
yet what we've just created here is
we've essentially allocated 200 bytes of
memory when you look at code like this
it's really important for you to kind of
think about what you're actually do
you're not in any way creating integers
whatsoever what you're doing is you're
basically just allocating memory and all
this this whole system of int and 50
that is just setting the size of the
allocation we know that an integer is 4
bytes and we know that we want 50 of
them so 50 times 4 is 200 so we're
allocating 200 bytes of memory that is
all this happening here nothing
nothing's being initialized nothing's
saying that Arkady's are integers
doesn't matter I could then proceed to
use this integer to store floats right
all this array to store floats it
doesn't matter what I've done what all
that I've done is I've allocated 200
bytes of memory that's it right so the
big thing here then if you look at this
is that these these applications are
actually identical what I've done here
is the same as what I've done here okay
all I've done is I've allocated 200
bytes of memory in both cases it's just
that when I start to deal with these for
example I say a 2d 0 equals whatever it
may call that's a different operation
right because if I address it like this
I'm talking about an integer whereas if
I address it like this I'm talking about
it matches your pointer because that's
the underlying type so that's kind of
step one to this whole process and
that's kind of my way of teaching C++ I
need you to realize what's actually
happening behind the scenes because
that's the only way you're going to get
good at using this language is by
knowing what's happening so that you can
then kind of play around with that and
change that so the big thing here is
again the type is just setting basically
the syntax that you can use to deal with
this data in the end it's 200 bytes
that's all that you dunk this stage so
what we want to achieve with our
two-dimensional array can assist in here
is now that we have room to store 200
bytes worth of pointers so 50 pointers
we can then go through and set each of
those pointers to point to an array and
that way what we actually end up with is
50 arrays right so we have an array of
arrays we have we have an array which
contains the memory locations of 50
arrays hopefully that makes sense so if
we go back here the way that we do this
is we loop through 50 times through this
a 2d array so we know that we have 50 of
them and then we say a 2d at I equals
new int 50 okay just like that so what
that's done let's get rid of that single
dimensional array here what we've done
here is we've essentially allocated 50
arrays and each one of those arrays the
location of each one of those arrays is
stored inside this a 2d array and that
is what a two-dimensional array is now
if you had a three-dimensional array you
have a nested followed so you'd go
through and you'd allocate you have to
allocate essentially you know the inner
level which is kind of one dimension
again it might be easier to just picture
like a cube or something or a grid kind
of cute' grid right and then just kind
of go through and picture filling up
each cell like you have to go through X
through Y and through Zed there'd be
three dimensions to that it'd be the
same he might actually just be easier
for me to show you so a three
dimensional array would look like this
we have a triple pointer here we'd be
allocating a pointer of pointers then
what we would what we would do here is
we know that we have 50 pointers to
pointers okay so this is getting a bit
more confusing so what we have to do
here is actually say I'll call this a 3d
we'd have to say a 3d at index I and
I'll actually change these to be
probably x and y maybe all I and J will
work as well so a 3d eye which is a
pointer by the way that's the point two
pointers would be equal to a new int
pointer allocation of 50 right so we
know how 50 of those and then for each
of these we also want to go through them
so upholds verbal J and allocate each of
these so a 3d eye our maze the same and
then this becomes J equals Neary and 50
okay so we've added another index here
because and I'll break this down a
little bit
so it's more easier to see because this
a 3d is appointed to a pointer to a
pointer so this is kind of dereferencing
the first part of that pointer and then
this is to referencing the second part
of that pointer so it'll be the same as
if I said let's get our a 2d from this
or our 2d kind of point in here so we'll
say PC R equals a 3d I right and then to
this a 3d I I'm going into oh sorry to
this point Oh what am I saying answered
ad which is pointer I'm actually saying
access that at index J and set that up
with 50 of those so this is a 3d 3d
allocation okay what we're doing here is
we've got 51 quote 50 I'm like confusing
myself by saying this I hope this is
making sense this is one of those cases
where you're gonna have to sit down
stare at this code maybe draw something
on a piece of paper and figure out how
it works because this is pretty
difficult to explain I'm not gonna lie
back to this there I'll give it one more
shot
so again what we have here is three
pointers okay well not three pointers
but a pointer to a pointer to a pointer
that's our type we've created what we've
done here is we've allocated 50 pointers
I might actually make a video on what
point is the point is mean because that
might be confusing in itself anyway
we've allocated 50 pointers to pointers
right we're going through each of those
pointers to pointers and creating an
array of pointers and then we're going
through each of those pointers because
what we have here is just normal array
of pointers and we're setting each of
those pointers to an actual array so
we're allocating our actual type here
int and this is what we would this is
the actual type allocation because this
is you know this is just a point around
occasion like we're allocating an array
of pointers here but here we're actually
allocating our array of integers and
then if we want to access this we'd have
to go a 3d and then kind of you know the
outer coordinate these middle coordinate
so X Y and then we'll save that and then
that's how we would set each one of
those okay so you can see that it
literally is a three dimensional array
because if we just take that that's
going to give us an array of pointers to
pointers and if we take that it's going
to give us an array of pointers and then
this is what actually gives us our
so hopefully that kind of makes sense
anyway back to the 2d example that it's
gonna be way easier to explain again 0
and then 0 this is the first element and
if you want to go to the second element
that's is like that the third element
like that you have to remember that this
row here is kind of the rightmost row
that is your actual integer that you're
accessing if you shift over and you take
a look at this column here that is just
that is the index of a pointer not of an
integer because that's this array that
you're actually dealing with that's what
this column is whereas this column on
the right here is actually this inner
array that you're dealing with okay so
that's two-dimensional arrays now when
it comes to deleting them which is what
we have to do as well if we keep
allocate them like this you have to go
through and iterate and delete all of
those arrays because you can't you can't
you can't just do it this if I go ahead
and I say delete and I do a 2d or
whatever like that sorry you can you'll
note by the way I typed that there
specifically you'll know that there is
no such thing as that operator so you
don't need to wait array like that if
you go ahead and you just do that do
that and you delete it what that's gonna
do is that's going to release this
memory which is just 200 bytes by the
memory it's just the array that holds
pointers to your actual integer arrays
so all of those 50 times 200 bytes that
you have there that is your actual data
there's all those 50 arrays they're now
gonna be a memory leak because we have
no way to access them we can't delete
them in the future cuz we just deleted
the array that held those pointers that
told us where those other arrays were so
what you actually have to do to delete
this is iterate through this 50 times
and delete a 2d at index I like that
that is what deletes it and then finally
you also have to delete a 2d so that's
kind of the reverse of that all right
hopefully that made at least a bit of
sense if you have questions please leave
them in the comments below and I I'm
sure I'll end up making videos this was
a hotter video to make and I'm not a
cleat done yes I'm gonna keep talking
for a bit what I've what I've said here
is that an array a two-dimensional array
or multi-dimensional arrays is an array
of arrays now here's my issue with this
whole thing apart from evidently being
really hard to deal with it's the fact
that when you're dealing with an array
of arrays you result in it that dis
results in memory fragmentation so what
I want here really and let's just again
I'm just gonna I don't know why one with
50 let's go with 5 that's a bit of a
more of a magical example to deal with
because we can actually picture 25
elements if we have an a what we have
here is an array of 5 arrays and each
one of those 5 arrays is an array of 5
integers so we have 25 integers 5 times
5 is 25
okay each instead of us having just one
continuous buffer that was capable
holding 25 integers just in a ROM in
memory what we've actually done is we've
created five separate buffers of five
integers each okay they're gonna be
allocated unless you're using some kind
of custom allocated order or an arena or
something like that they're gonna be
allocated and completely random places
in memory they might be close together
there there might not be nothing
guarantees they're gonna be close
together that's an issue because if we
have to iterate through an access agent
those 25 integers
every time we iterate through five
integers and we go to the next row of
our array or our next dimension
basically we drop down to our next
integer array we have to jump to another
location in memory to read to access
that data to read or write that data and
that's the results probably in a cache
miss which means that we're wasting time
fetching that from our actual RAM it
might not be a cache miss if they happen
to be allocated close together but again
there's nothing for us to we can't rely
on them being allocated close together
they're most likely not going to be so
because of that it's actually going to
be slower a lot slower a lot slower to
iterate through
these 25 integers this way then if I had
just allocated a single dimensional
array of 25 integers in a row in memory
because that memory is going to be all
in a row and one of the most important
things when you're programming and
you're optimizing and you're dealing
with memory well one of the most
important things you can do to optimize
is actually optimize your memory
accessing so if you can store memory
close together that you'll be accessing
and you can kind of actually position it
in a way that results in more cache hits
and less cache misses your program will
perform faster and we're definitely
going to learn more about caching and
health of CPU cache works and all that
in the future this is kind of a good way
I think to introduce it now people say
well I need a two dimensional array
there's no other way to deal with it
right wrong you've got 25 integers here
that's what you've made you've made an
array of 5 integers 5 times that's 25
integers can you really not think of a
better way to store 25 integers you can
just store them in a single dimensional
array look I'll show you what you can do
here is just make an array of 5 times 5
integers okay okay so let's just say I
want to set all these integers - I don't
know - so I'd have to iterate through
them this way we'll say for in form y
equals 0 Y is less than 5 y plus + and
then we'll have to so that iterates
through our array of pointers and then
we'll go in the inner loop changes to X
and we'll get array through the actual
arrays and we'll say a 2d XY equals - ok
that's how I set it you know like this
is cool though because it's like I've
got a 2d grid and I can be like oh yeah
index you know X is 2 y is 3 like it's
really easy to deal with like that well
you can do the same thing here I mean
obviously if you wanted to set
everything to 2 in this array all you
really would have to do is just say for
n I 0 is less than 25 or 5 times 5 I
plus plus and then array I equals - easy
mr. easy right but you could also write
it this way and then it's just instead
of doing that you just say X plus y
times the width of your array which is
five so this kind of dimension over here
right or this dimension it doesn't
really matter what doesn't matter
because it's your width if you have a
grid this is your width because what
you're saying here is you're saying that
every time the Y increments I want you
to jump five elements forward which
would be the equivalent I'm just
dropping down a row if you had your grid
okay we can talk about this in more
detail if you would like leave a comment
below I'll see what kind of what your
thoughts are it's hard for me to gauge
where you guys are at this point like
you are like I mean I know that
obviously a lot of people with very
varying kind of skill sets watch these
videos but now that you know that
there's like 50 plus of these videos I
feel like you guys are kind of like my
class on my students and I really want
to know where you're at so if you don't
understand this stuff and you want me to
explain it with diagrams in a bit more a
bit more then I'll definitely do that
anyway so that's kind of the idea here
you can see that I can access this
exactly the same way as a
two-dimensional array but guess what
this code is actually a lot faster than
this code because this code every five
every time we go to this outer for loop
has to jump to a completely different
array in memory or if this is just
accessing that same memory that's all in
a row in our actual memory so I
personally avoid 2d arrays as much as
possible sometimes it makes a lot of
sense to use them unless the time it
doesn't okay if I was storing a bitmap
for example and I had all the pixels in
an image you might think of an image
like a photo like a texture as a 2d
thing right like you've got pixels and
it's like a - it is like a 2d grid right
so I should store it as a 2d array right
no store it is a single dimensional
array it doesn't matter that you can't
like you can still it doesn't matter how
you story you can start as a
two-dimensional array or a
one-dimensional array but the
one-dimensional right way is gonna be
the much much much more optimal way of
actually storing that image anyway I
hope you guys enjoyed watching this
video if you didn't hit the like button
you can also help support the series by
going a patriotic involves laughter the
cherry
huge thank you to all the patrons that
make this series possible because it
wouldn't be here without you if you want
the plenty of critical rewards for
supporting the series such as getting
like a monthly hang out with all the
other supporters of that tier as well as
source code access to my opengl series
and like a private discord like channel
where we can talk about stuff and
there's plenty of stuff there and it
really does help support the series so
thank you so much those people yeah
I'm really interested with this video to
see what you guys think so leave a
comment below and I'll see you in the
next video goodbye
[Music]